<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: So long and thanks for all the fish | Mavnn's blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/blog/categories/so-long-and-thanks-for-all-the-fish/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2020-03-20T20:35:10+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[mavnn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Beginnings and Endings]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/beginnings-and-endings/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-26T12:02:10+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/beginnings-and-endings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&#39;s the normal mix of excitement and sadness as I announce that today is my last day with my current employers, <a href="http://www.15below.com">15below</a>.</p>

<p>Sadness because the people here are great and I&#39;ve learned an unbelievable amount while working here. Excitement because there&#39;s
exciting things happening for the future. What are these brave new vistas? Well, that will have to wait for next week.</p>

<p>But for now, it&#39;s time for a brief thank you and review of what I&#39;m leaving.</p>

<p>Thanks 15below for:</p>

<ul>
<li>being an incredibly flexible, generous &amp; family friendly employer</li>
<li>Lots and lots of learning from existing code, conversations, other people delivering internal training, <a href="https://twitter.com/15below_travel/status/340475764677951488">letting me invite external speakers</a>, and the rest</li>
<li>releasing some open source, even while in an &quot;enterprise&quot; market: <a href="https://github.com/15below/">github</a></li>
<li>letting me <a href="https//blog.mavnn.co.uk/keeping-up-with-the-latest-hammer/">coordinate the internal developer education</a></li>
<li>sponsoring a <a href="https//blog.mavnn.co.uk/functional-programming-in-an-imperitive-world/">bunch</a> <a href="https//blog.mavnn.co.uk/sdd-conf-2015/">of</a>
<a href="https//blog.mavnn.co.uk/lambdacon-2015/">conference</a> speaking (there&#39;s more!)</li>
<li>trusting me to convert the build from msbuild to <a href="https://github.com/fsharp/FAKE">FAKE</a> and kick start the journey to automated deployment (which was a slow and painful one in msbuild world...)</li>
<li>picking solid, generous people <a href="https://www.facebook.com/15below/posts/829520247132711">as staff</a> - that&#39;s just one example from many, and the company often matches the giving of the staff</li>
</ul>

<p>I&#39;m hoping my last piece of work here, converting our main product repository to use <a href="http://fsprojects.github.io/Paket/">Paket</a> rather than nuget for dependency management is a gift that will keep on giving to the rest of the devs; here&#39;s to many more years of 15below bringing tech to the travel industry.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
