<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mavnn ltd | Mavnn's blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/blog/categories/mavnn-ltd/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2020-03-20T20:35:10+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[mavnn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Level Up Your F# Skills]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/level-up-your-f-number-skills/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-06T10:20:01+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/level-up-your-f-number-skills</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>@mavnn ltd have always offered training as a service, but we&#39;re now pleased
to announce our very first public training event. As readers of this blog (or people attending <a href="https://skillsmatter.com/conferences/8053-f-sharp-exchange-2017#skillscasts">F# Exchange</a>), you
get first notification!</p>

<p>&quot;Level Up Your F#&quot; is going to be a two day course running in London on the 15th-16th June.
We&#39;ll run through a syllabus of language features unique to F# and not shared by
the other dotnet languages - features that offer unparalleled expressive power 
at the cost of a learning curve and the occasional sharp edge. In the course we&#39;ll
give you a leg up that curve, and protect you from a few cuts along the way.</p>

<p>This course will be aimed at people who have spent some time coding in F#
(possibly after taking a course like the &quot;<a href="https://skillsmatter.com/courses/473-tomas-petricek-phil-trelford-fast-track-to-fsharp#overview">Fast Track to F#</a>&quot;) and realise that their
projects could benefit from a deeper understanding of F# special
abilities. These techniques are especially useful for writing generic,
reusable code - whether that&#39;s core internal code or widely used libraries.</p>

<p>It will be a small group, allowing for personalization and some flexibility in design,
but at its core it will be build up through four major topics:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Useful tricks: active patterns, member constraints, etc</p></li>
<li><p>Quotations: what they are, and how and when to use them</p></li>
<li><p>Type Providers: how to build them, and use them for type safety</p></li>
<li><p>Computational Expressions: build powerful abstractions and then expose them in an easy to use way</p></li>
</ol>

<p>We&#39;re aiming for a cost of £1,295.00 for the course with early bird (<strike>10</strike> 15% until the 15th May) and group discounts available (contact <a href="mailto:us@mavnn.co.uk">us</a>). Due to the nature of the course, there will be a hard limit of 12 attendees. There&#39;s also a limited quantity of super-early bird tickets available if you&#39;re quick! Register your interest soon to secure a ticket, and if there&#39;s a waiting list we&#39;ll consult you about
additional dates.</p>

<p>As always with @mavnn training courses, we&#39;re also willing to come and deliver this training on site and tailor it to your specific needs. Contact us at <a href="mailto:us@mavnn.co.uk">us@mavnn.co.uk</a> to discuss requirements and quotes.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h3>Details:</h3>

<h2>How do I book?</h2>

<p>You can book right here! :)</p>

<div style="width:100%; text-align:left;"><iframe src="https://blog.mavnn.co.uk//eventbrite.co.uk/tickets-external?eid=33720450776&ref=etckt" frameborder="0" height="478" width="100%" vspace="0" hspace="0" marginheight="5" marginwidth="5" scrolling="auto" allowtransparency="true"></iframe><div style="font-family:Helvetica, Arial; font-size:12px; padding:10px 0 5px; margin:2px; width:100%; text-align:left;" ><a class="powered-by-eb" style="color: #ADB0B6; text-decoration: none;" target="_blank" href="http://www.eventbrite.co.uk/">Powered by Eventbrite</a></div></div>

<p>If your ad/privacy blocker doesn&#39;t like the embedded widget, you can also book direct on <a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/level-up-your-f-skills-tickets-33720450776">eventbrite</a>.</p>

<h2>Prerequisites</h2>

<p>We will expect attendees to be familiar with F# syntax, including the use of discriminated unions and computational expressions such as async. Other concepts will be explained and explored during the course.</p>

<h2>What to bring</h2>

<p>You will need to bring your own computer with a F# development environment already
installed. VS Code, Visual Studio, Vim, other editor that doesn&#39;t begin with &quot;V&quot;: 
all are fine as long as you can write and compile F# code on the machine. Extra drink
token for anyone who brings a Raspberry Pi as their dev environment!</p>

<h2>What you&#39;ll get</h2>

<p>2 days of workshops guiding you through the unique features of F#, along with code
and exercises to take away with you.</p>

<p>Breakfast, coffee, lunch, and dinner provided within the course costing including
a round of drinks for the evening of the first day.</p>

<h2>Where will it be</h2>

<p>At the <a href="https://wellcomecollection.org/">Wellcome Collection</a>, right next to Euston Station.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annoucing @mavnn ltd]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/annoucing-at-mavnn-ltd/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-07T10:23:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/annoucing-at-mavnn-ltd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I hinted in the last post, new (and to me) exciting things are afoot. I&#39;m very pleased
to announce the formation of <a href="http://mavnn.co.uk">@mavnn ltd</a>!</p>

<h3>That&#39;s great, but what is it going to do?</h3>

<p>I&#39;m glad you asked! @mavnn ltd is the continuation of a lot of the things I&#39;ve come to care most about over my years in software development: building reliable, maintainable and well crafted code and teaching others to do the same.</p>

<p>You can check out the web page for more details, but basically there&#39;s three streams to what the company will be providing:</p>

<ul>
<li>Building code that works</li>
<li>Offering consultancy on how your team can build better software with less friction (especially around automating build, deployment and testing)</li>
<li>Giving training in skills that will allow teams to build solid software using functional programming techniques and thinking</li>
</ul>

<h3>What are doing already?</h3>

<p>I&#39;m glad you asked that too! Stream one of the company (&quot;Building code that works&quot;) is already well under way - we&#39;re very pleased to say that @mavnn ltd&#39;s first customer is <a href="https://github.com/logibit">Logibit</a>, where I&#39;m helping Henrik and Mikko build out the <a href="https://qvitoo.com/">Qvitoo</a> platform.</p>

<p>Although it&#39;s always nice as a small company to have contracts, we&#39;re particularly pleased to be working with Logibit: firstly because they&#39;re great people to work with - you don&#39;t need to work for them to find that out, just get involved in any of the myriad <a href="http://suave.io/">open</a> <a href="https://github.com/Albacore/albacore">source</a> <a href="https://github.com/logary/logary">projects</a> they&#39;re involved in!</p>

<p>Secondly, as a company they embody the things that @mavnn stands for: leveraging the ideas behind functional programming in deeply practical ways to build software that solves real world problems, and does so exactly as designed.</p>

<h3>Can I hire you?</h3>

<p>Yes! To avoid disappointment, though, I should make it clear that we have some ongoing contractual agreements and so will not be accepting ongoing full time contracts for the foreseeable future.</p>

<p>Training, consultancy, ongoing part time and short term full time contracts are all up for grabs though - including remotely and in some cases internationally as evidenced by our co-operation with Logibit. <a href="http://mavnn.co.uk/#contacts">Contact us to find out more</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
