<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Theology | Mavnn's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.mavnn.co.uk/blog/categories/theology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.mavnn.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-05T14:31:20+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.mavnn.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[mavnn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Being a priest and programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.mavnn.co.uk/being-a-priest-and-programming/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-29T20:19:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.mavnn.co.uk/being-a-priest-and-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>But you are a chosen people, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, God’s special possession, that you may declare the praises of him who called you out of darkness into his wonderful light. <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20Peter+2:9&amp;version=NIV">(1 Peter 2:9)</a></p></blockquote>

<p>Warning: this post may contain theology and other non-programming related
material. You have been warned&hellip;</p>

<p><a href="http://hrbc.org.uk">Our church</a> started a new sermon series last week, and as the
sermon was going on various other bits and pieces came together in my mind, and
I knew that I was going to have to at least try and get them down in writing or
they were going to run around my head for the next few days.</p>

<p>It comes up regularly for us as Christians that God isn&rsquo;t small enough to be
contained to Sunday mornings &ndash; he wants a larger part of our lives than that,
in fact the central part. But the idea of worshipping God with your whole
life often begins to get a bit weird when you actually stop and think about it.
Worship (&lsquo;to assign worth to something&rsquo;) is not a strange idea to any of us,
although we might not use that language &ndash; I&rsquo;m sure you can all think of a
respected author, favourite footballer or awe inspiring musician. And if you
buy into the whole Christian idea of who and what God is (infinitely powerful
and awesomely loving, perfect judge who offers grace, amazing sense of humour)
then the idea that a Christian is going to worship God also shouldn&rsquo;t seem that
strange.</p>

<p>But with your whole life? There&rsquo;s <a href="http://biblia.com/bible/esv/Romans%2012.1%E2%80%932">no doubt</a>
<a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Deuteronomy+6&amp;version=NIV">biblically</a>
or in the teachings of both <a href="http://www.desiringgod.org/resource-library/sermons/all-of-life-as-worship">Christian teachers</a>
and <a href="http://www.jewfaq.org/prayer/shema.htm">Jewish tradition</a> that this is
precisely what is expected of us. But&hellip; when you write computer code as a day
job, what does that actually mean?</p>

<p>And then it struck me. It means being a <a href="https://people.gnome.org/~michael/">Michael Meeks</a> or a <a href="https://twitter.com/jonskeet/status/8423111419">Jon Skeet</a>. Probably not in the
specific details &ndash; I&rsquo;ve not met either of them personally, but in the attitude
they show to life and the people around them. If you&rsquo;re not in the programming
field (probably, if you don&rsquo;t happen to be in a similar area of the programming
field to me&hellip;) you&rsquo;re not likely to have heard of them. But they&rsquo;ve both
developed an enormous amount of respect in a field that is frequently full of
highly opinionated staunch atheists while being openly professing Christians.</p>

<p>So we wrap round to where we started &ndash; the idea from 1 Peter of
all Christians being priests. (I&rsquo;m not using the term here in the catholic
sense, so bear with me&hellip;). This comes up a lot when people relate one of the
core Christian doctrines &ndash; that people who have come into a relation with
Christ can come directly to God without an intermediary. But that wasn&rsquo;t the only
role of priests in the Old Testament. Yes, they were the only people who could
enter God&rsquo;s presence&hellip; but they weren&rsquo;t only going there for themselves. They
<em>were</em> the intermediaries, &lsquo;introducing&rsquo; others to God&rsquo;s presence, carrying
blessings from God to them and petitions from them to God.</p>

<p>Jon and Michael are dedicated to
what they do, they are good at it and they are &lsquo;graceful&rsquo;. In the sense that
they treat the people around them with respect and as professionals, teaching
and helping without regard to the others faith and without forcing argument and
discussion where it&rsquo;s not wanted. Both are obviously willing to talk to people
who want to (Michael even links to a fun page on <a href="http://christianthinktank.com/objedex.html">Christian Think Tank</a> for those who are
interested), but there isn&rsquo;t a pressure there.</p>

<p>And maybe that&rsquo;s what some small part of everyday worship looks like; I can&rsquo;t help feeling that by
being respectable (in the sense of, worthy of some respect) and making the fact
of their faith public, people like Jon and Michael have been doing their bit to
draw others closer to this God I worship. They&rsquo;ve caused a doubt and a second
look at what faith really means in the mind of those who would otherwise live
in an atheist bubble, carelessly dismissing the idea of God as the ramblings of
the obviously stupid and insane. Because these men are clearly neither.</p>

<p>This is encouraging to me, and I hope to a lot of out there who go to work, work hard
and tell people that you made it to church this Sunday. Because if you look
around you&rsquo;ll probably begin to see these people around you, the Jons and Michaels
who are making a difference just by living a life based on Christ&rsquo;s in the everyday.</p>

<p>And guess what? If you&rsquo;re a Christian, letting people know without pressure and
getting your coding/plumbing/teaching/building/etc. done you&rsquo;re probably making a difference
too. You might be the last to see
it, but I&rsquo;m sure others do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
