<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rule the world | Mavnn's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.mavnn.co.uk/blog/categories/rule-the-world/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.mavnn.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-06T15:21:14+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.mavnn.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[mavnn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[If I Ruled the World... Remote Working]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.mavnn.co.uk/remote-working/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-15T20:43:06+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.mavnn.co.uk/remote-working</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to a new category of posts for my blog. It&rsquo;s the &ldquo;Rule the World&rdquo; category, where I spout opinions on a subject with gay abandon, even if I can&rsquo;t actually offer that much beyond anecdotal evidence to back the opinion up.</p>

<p>On this occasion I even feel justified as someone has actively asked my opinion about something.</p>

<p>Well, that was foolish now, wasn&rsquo;t it?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>In the Blue Corner</h2>

<p>These questions are coming from a friend who is heading up the development team of a small but reasonably established start up in London. Hiring is competitive, wages are high, and all of their production services are running in a remote data center somewhere else anyway.</p>

<p>He&rsquo;d also like to be able to go surfing before work some mornings, which is hard in central London.</p>

<p>All of this has lead to an interest in both remote working and working from home.</p>

<h2>In the Red Corner</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve never been a fully remote worker, but for family reasons I&rsquo;ve been working somewhere between one and two days a week from home for about 6 years now. I&rsquo;ve also worked occasional periods of a week or two completely remotely. I&rsquo;ve therefore lived one of the scenarios that is concern to my surfing friend: can you mix and match remote/home working and office based workers, or do you have to really go the whole hog and be a fully distributed company if you want to open up the
option at all?</p>

<h2>Let&rsquo;s get started!</h2>

<p>The questions were originally sent to me by email, which I asked for permission to reproduce here, slightly reformatted and with a few bits redacted to protect the potentially innocent:</p>

<blockquote><p>At [our company] the &ldquo;default&rdquo; is very much in the office. I want to actively encourage/enable people to work remotely without it evolving into a &ldquo;second class&rdquo; citizen? Partly because I think it&rsquo;s a &ldquo;good&rdquo; thing, and so we can genuinely hire the best possible talent. And the longer the company exists the harder it will be to establish that culture. I for one would like to try surfing in the morning and working later&hellip; and I can&rsquo;t do that in London!</p>

<p>Current tools/workflow:</p>

<ul>
<li>We all use [chat software] already &ndash; I <em>think</em> we&rsquo;ll just need more discipline to ensure as much chat as possible is on [chat software] even if it&rsquo;s discussed in the office.</li>
<li>All dev goes through pull requests, which should work fine remotely too. We&rsquo;ve experimented with ScreenHero for pair programming, which in theory would work though haven&rsquo;t tried more than once or twice.</li>
</ul>


<p>Current unknowns:</p>

<ul>
<li>Are we talking working remotely, but commutable in to the office, or genuinely distributed team? Pros/cons.</li>
<li>Core working hours? How do we deal with non-devs and ensuring we have customer support covered as a company?</li>
<li>More ad-hoc catch ups? How to deal with weekly planning/priorities?</li>
<li>What kinds of machines do we buy people? Currently they&rsquo;re fast desktops, but you won&rsquo;t get the same spec on a laptop unless it&rsquo;s a brick. Jon is experimenting with top of the range 15" macbook, but personally I wouldn&rsquo;t want to lug that to the office either.</li>
<li>Web cams / other things like Sqwiggle? Do we care?</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>There&rsquo;s a fair amount of stuff there, so let&rsquo;s start knocking questions out :).</p>

<p>Starting with the easy ones first&hellip;</p>

<h2>Kit</h2>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>What kinds of machines do we buy people? Currently they&rsquo;re fast desktops, but you won&rsquo;t get the same spec on a laptop unless it&rsquo;s a brick. Jon is experimenting with top of the range 15" macbook, but personally I wouldn&rsquo;t want to lug that to the office either.</li>
<li>Web cams / other things like Sqwiggle? Do we care?</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>I do a fair amount of heavy dev work as part of my current job. My working from home kit? A <a href="http://shop.lenovo.com/gb/en/laptops/lenovo/yoga/yoga-13/#tab-tech_specs">Yoga IdeaPad</a> and a headset. It&rsquo;s a relatively high end model, and I&rsquo;d probably recommend the ThinkPad version now it exists, but really &ndash; it&rsquo;s good enough.</p>

<p>Between having an SSD and 8gb of RAM, you can easily run several copies of Visual Studio, a couple of virtual machines and all your normal background apps (email, chat, browser, etc) without noticeable slow down. It&rsquo;s light weight, has a long battery life and is comfortable to use on the move. I&rsquo;m with Hanselman &ndash; <a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/MyNextPCWillBeAnUltrabook.aspx">the ultrabook has arrived</a> as a development environment, and that was two years ago.</p>

<p>Is it slower than the desktop the guy next to me uses? Yes. Do I notice in day to day, even heavy weight development? No.</p>

<p>As a bonus, most ultrabooks also have a web cam built in. But you want the headset. Oh, yes. You want the headset.</p>

<p>For small groups at least, Google Hangouts or Skype appear to work pretty well. I&rsquo;ve not had reason to try anything heavier weight, although I could see some of the pair programming tools being helpful.</p>

<h2>Core working hours</h2>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>Core working hours? How do we deal with non-devs and ensuring we have customer support covered as a company?</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>&hellip;rant mode: on&hellip;</strong></p>

<p>So: <a href="http://heeris.id.au/2013/this-is-why-you-shouldnt-interrupt-a-programmer/">you</a> <a href="http://lifehacker.com/how-to-stay-productive-in-an-open-working-environment-1443536319">shouldn&rsquo;t</a> <a href="http://mattrogish.com/blog/2012/03/17/open-plan-offices-must-die/">interrupt</a> <a href="http://www.thesoundagency.com/2011/sound-news/more-damaging-evidence-on-open-plan-offices/">programmers</a>. Those are just the first few results on Google, I haven&rsquo;t even started digging into the actual
scientific references.</p>

<p><strong>&hellip;rant mode: off&hellip;</strong></p>

<p>Given that you&rsquo;re not interrupting your programmers, what do you want? Well &ndash; you want asynchronous communication channels (chat, email) for when your programmer choose to interrupt themselves and you want at least each person to have at least one time a day when they&rsquo;re online with a group simultaneously. I was going to say when you have everyone on at the same time, but I&rsquo;m not actually sure that&rsquo;s a prerequisite.</p>

<p>One thing I&rsquo;ve often felt working from home in an environment where it isn&rsquo;t the norm is the pressure to &ldquo;appear to be online&rdquo; in the same way that there&rsquo;s the pressure to be &ldquo;sitting at the desk&rdquo; when you&rsquo;re in the office. In reality, both are stupid; you&rsquo;ll get better code out of me between 8pm and 10pm if I&rsquo;ve taken 3pm-5pm off to pick up my son from school and spend some time with him. In the same way, you&rsquo;ll get better code out of me after I&rsquo;ve nipped out of
the office to get a coffee than if I sit at my desk pretending to be productive when I&rsquo;m stuck on a difficult mental problem.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s hard to judge how much of this pressure is real, and how much is in my head. But if I ruled the world, er, company, the lack of core hours would be explicit.</p>

<p>Are there exceptions to this? Yes, especially during planning phases of projects where it&rsquo;s helpful to have more people on at the same time more often. Also, as mentioned above, support isn&rsquo;t something you can turn on and off depending who happens to be online. You might not be able to allow unpredictable working hours; but that doesn&rsquo;t mean everyone has to have the same working hours.</p>

<h2>There isn&rsquo;t a water cooler!</h2>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>More ad-hoc catch ups? How to deal with weekly planning/priorities?</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Ok, so I miss white boards when I&rsquo;m not in the office.</p>

<p>Having said that, because we don&rsquo;t like interrupting each other too much, in practice the teams I&rsquo;ve worked best with have done a great deal of their catching up via chat <em>even when they&rsquo;ve all been sitting next to each other</em>. Why? No interruptions, instant record of decisions.</p>

<p>When I&rsquo;m in the office, I do take advantage of being able to call someone over and point at the screen. It&rsquo;s a genuine downside of not being physically present that you can&rsquo;t do that when you&rsquo;re working remotely, but screen sharing tech covers most of the same ground.</p>

<h2>How does it work?</h2>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>Are we talking working remotely, but commutable in to the office, or genuinely distributed team? Pros/cons.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>I&rsquo;ve deliberately left the most interesting question till last.</p>

<p>All of the places where I&rsquo;ve regularly worked from home have been primarily office based organisations (two have been local councils). This has had some consequences on occasion.</p>

<p>Most importantly, if you want fully remote workers and you want them to feel involved my experience suggests you will have to work <strong>hard</strong> at it to make it work. As someone who works from home some of the time, I often find I&rsquo;ve missed things when I&rsquo;ve been out of the office because they didn&rsquo;t make it onto chat or email but I then spot them when I come back in. But for me, that&rsquo;s a delay of just a day or two. For a fully remote worker, that content is just lost. The exchange
is that on the days I&rsquo;m out of the office I feel I get a lot more done, especially if I&rsquo;m working on heavily conceptual problems, and it adds an extra flexibility to the home work balance exchange that makes it massively easier to stay sane. In fact, at times (with a young child and a wife who was suffering from a chronic health condition) it has been the only way I could work full time hours. The overhead of the commute and more fixed working times would have left me unable to
get close to full time otherwise.</p>

<p>This might make it sound like I&rsquo;m claiming that the ideal is people who regularly commute into the office, and regularly work from home. And we&rsquo;ll just ignore all those hard issues with fully remote workers and building in all that deliberate extra communication.</p>

<p>But actually, I&rsquo;m not convinced.</p>

<p>Why not?</p>

<p>1) <em>That extra communication is useful anyway.</em> A lot of this stuff is things that should really, <strong>really</strong> be written down regardless, but we&rsquo;re human so we don&rsquo;t bother if there isn&rsquo;t an immediate reason.</p>

<p>2) <em>There is a high possibility you&rsquo;ll end up with fully remote workers anyway.</em> I nearly moved to Italy this year to help look after my elderly parents-in-law. If I had, I wouldn&rsquo;t have wanted to stop working for my current employer, and they didn&rsquo;t really want to let me go. And then you have the whole 24 hour support question &ndash; doesn&rsquo;t just setting up an Australian office make more sense? (Which is, in fact, what the current company have ended up doing.)</p>

<p>3) <em>You&rsquo;re already paying for the infrastructure &ndash; but not getting the cost benefits.</em> If you want to allow people to work from home, there are some cost implications. You&rsquo;ll probably want a VPN, possibly phone forwarding, etc. But you&rsquo;re still paying everyone a full London salary. And you&rsquo;ve still got as many desks as you used to. You&rsquo;re not getting all the pain, but you&rsquo;re not getting all the benefits either.</p>

<p>4) <em>Talent.</em> Not all the clever people live in [substitute your town/country here]. Most programming communities are full of online, highly English literate people (almost by definition) who <em>do not live where you do</em>. Why waste the opportunity?</p>

<p>On a more general note, things that have helped or hurt my remote working:</p>

<ul>
<li>A sensible VPN set up is great; don&rsquo;t make me bounce Spotify over <em>your</em> bandwidth.</li>
<li>Speaking of which: a basic build shouldn&rsquo;t require you to be on the VPN. Some of the integration tests may need it, but a basic build shouldn&rsquo;t. An unreliable VPN connection should be a minor inconvenience, not a reason to pack up and play tennis.</li>
<li>Video chat is sometimes nice &ndash; text based chat is invaluable. Text based chat <strong>should not go through the VPN</strong>. It&rsquo;s how you tell people the VPN isn&rsquo;t working. You might think I&rsquo;ve experienced some VPN issues over the years, I couldn&rsquo;t possibly comment.</li>
<li>If there are a group based in an office, it&rsquo;s worth investing in some kit. Having tried it, trying to have a multi-party video chat with headsets where two or more people are in the same room is painful. Get the group microphone/speaker with noise cancellation, it&rsquo;s worth it.</li>
</ul>


<h2>So &ndash; if I ruled the world&hellip;</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;d be looking at making sure that my company was fully remote worker friendly, even if I didn&rsquo;t have remote workers yet. And I&rsquo;d be doing it as early as possible.</p>

<p>YMMV :)</p>

<p>(especially if you&rsquo;re not running a software house, which I&rsquo;ve kind of assumed here)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
