<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: qvitoo | Mavnn's blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/blog/categories/qvitoo/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2020-03-20T20:35:10+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[mavnn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annoucing @mavnn ltd]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/annoucing-at-mavnn-ltd/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-07T10:23:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/annoucing-at-mavnn-ltd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I hinted in the last post, new (and to me) exciting things are afoot. I&#39;m very pleased
to announce the formation of <a href="http://mavnn.co.uk">@mavnn ltd</a>!</p>

<h3>That&#39;s great, but what is it going to do?</h3>

<p>I&#39;m glad you asked! @mavnn ltd is the continuation of a lot of the things I&#39;ve come to care most about over my years in software development: building reliable, maintainable and well crafted code and teaching others to do the same.</p>

<p>You can check out the web page for more details, but basically there&#39;s three streams to what the company will be providing:</p>

<ul>
<li>Building code that works</li>
<li>Offering consultancy on how your team can build better software with less friction (especially around automating build, deployment and testing)</li>
<li>Giving training in skills that will allow teams to build solid software using functional programming techniques and thinking</li>
</ul>

<h3>What are doing already?</h3>

<p>I&#39;m glad you asked that too! Stream one of the company (&quot;Building code that works&quot;) is already well under way - we&#39;re very pleased to say that @mavnn ltd&#39;s first customer is <a href="https://github.com/logibit">Logibit</a>, where I&#39;m helping Henrik and Mikko build out the <a href="https://qvitoo.com/">Qvitoo</a> platform.</p>

<p>Although it&#39;s always nice as a small company to have contracts, we&#39;re particularly pleased to be working with Logibit: firstly because they&#39;re great people to work with - you don&#39;t need to work for them to find that out, just get involved in any of the myriad <a href="http://suave.io/">open</a> <a href="https://github.com/Albacore/albacore">source</a> <a href="https://github.com/logary/logary">projects</a> they&#39;re involved in!</p>

<p>Secondly, as a company they embody the things that @mavnn stands for: leveraging the ideas behind functional programming in deeply practical ways to build software that solves real world problems, and does so exactly as designed.</p>

<h3>Can I hire you?</h3>

<p>Yes! To avoid disappointment, though, I should make it clear that we have some ongoing contractual agreements and so will not be accepting ongoing full time contracts for the foreseeable future.</p>

<p>Training, consultancy, ongoing part time and short term full time contracts are all up for grabs though - including remotely and in some cases internationally as evidenced by our co-operation with Logibit. <a href="http://mavnn.co.uk/#contacts">Contact us to find out more</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
