<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: being human | Mavnn's blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/blog/categories/being-human/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2020-03-20T20:35:10+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[mavnn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deliberate Poster: Fighting Imposter Syndrome]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/deliberate-poster-fighting-imposter-syndrome/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-24T12:01:11+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.mavnn.co.uk/deliberate-poster-fighting-imposter-syndrome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I first became aware of Imposter Syndrome via an excellent <a href="https://www.hanselman.com/blog/ImAPhonyAreYou.aspx">blog post by Scott Hanselman</a>, but it immediately struck true.
I&#39;m a self taught programmer who dropped out of a Maths degree, and even now with years of experience that voice is there at the back of my head:</p>

<ul>
<li>&quot;You still make off by one errors, and you think you can train people?&quot;</li>
<li>&quot;How could you have let that bug slip by? It&#39;s obvious, I thought you knew what you were doing?&quot;</li>
<li>&quot;You want people to pay you for this? How exactly are you justifying that one to yourself?&quot;</li>
</ul>

<p>Normally I just try and tell it to shut up: everyone makes mistakes sometimes, I deliver stuff people get value from, etc.</p>

<p>But a few days back, something interesting happened. I&#39;d hit a problem that looked like it should be simple, and I&#39;d been bashing my head against it for a couple of days.
The imposter critic was out in force: &quot;call yourself a coder?&quot;. So I stepped back, took a deep breath, told the voice to stuff it and did the sensible thing. I asked my
co-director (and wife) for help.</p>

<p>Now, this isn&#39;t asking a random person off the street for assistance. She has a high level post-graduate degree in mathematics, is ridiculously good at spotting patterns and logical deduction
and has done some programming in the past herself (of the type you do during a maths degree).</p>

<p>It took me over an hour to explain what the actual problem was.</p>

<p>And as I dived through the OO patterns, domain specific knowledge and implementation constraints that built up into this &quot;simple&quot; problem it occurred to me that maybe I
had learnt something over the years. That maybe I wasn&#39;t as much of an imposter as the voice was trying to tell me. That possibly, just maybe, not being able to solve this
problem, right here, right now, didn&#39;t make me less valuable as a person or less competent as a professional. That the very fact I <em>had this problem</em> was actually evidence
that I had a clue what I was doing, or else I wouldn&#39;t have been able to get here.</p>

<p>So, a technique for all the &quot;imposters&quot; out there when the voice fires up: be deliberate in reminding yourself that you&#39;re actually a poster. Don&#39;t fight the voice with
generalities (even if they&#39;re true) - fight it with specifics.</p>

<p>Even if the specifics are &quot;2 years ago I didn&#39;t know enough to get myself into this mess&quot;.</p>

<p>And you know the bonus extra of this technique? It fights <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect">Dunning-Kruger</a> too...</p>

<p>I&#39;ll just be leaving this post lying around here so that my wife can post me a link to it next time I&#39;m in the imposter blues.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
